<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A heauenly voyce A sermon tending to call the people of God from among the Romish Babylonians: preached at Paules Crosse the 12 of Ianuarie. 1606. By William Symonds.</title>
            <author>Symonds, William, 1556-1616?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 67 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13287</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23591</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100150</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836002</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836002</idno>
            <idno type="VID">241</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13287)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 241)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1294:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A heauenly voyce A sermon tending to call the people of God from among the Romish Babylonians: preached at Paules Crosse the 12 of Ianuarie. 1606. By William Symonds.</title>
                  <author>Symonds, William, 1556-1616?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[36] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I[ames] R[oberts] for Edmund VVeauer, and are to be solde at his shoppe, at the great north-doore of Paules Church,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-E⁴.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 23591a on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Union Theological Seminary (New York, N.Y.). Library.</note>
                  <note>Leaf C2 stained; some print show-through.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A HEAVENLY Voyce.</p>
            <p>A Sermon tending to call the people of God from among the Romiſh <hi>Babylonians:</hi> Preached at Paules Croſſe the 12 of Ianuarie. 1606.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By William Symonds.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Epheſians.</hi> 5.11.</bibl>
               <p>Haue no fellowſhippe with the vnfruitfull workes of darkneſſe, but euen reprooue them rather.</p>
            </q>
            <p>At London Printed by I. R. for <hi>Edmund VVea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer,</hi> and are to be ſolde at his ſhoppe, at the great North-doore of Paules Church. 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="printer_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:241:2"/>
            <head>The Printer to the Reader.</head>
            <p>Gentle Reader, this Sermon came to my hands without any Title giuen to it by the Author. I haue therefore, of my ſelfe, aduentured to take a Title for it out of the firſt words of the Text, calling it a <hi>heauenly Voyce.</hi> This would I admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, to ſtop the mouthes of ſuch as happilie might cauill or her at it, or the Author for it.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:241:2"/>
            <head>To the right Honorable and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, <hi>Richard Vaughan,</hi> Doctor of Diuinitie, and Lord Biſhoppe of London, my very good Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">R</seg>Ight Honorable and</hi> reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes,</hi> vpon the <hi>top of Piſgah,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut, 34, 1, &amp; 3, 27.</note> did view the <hi>Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphie</hi> of the promiſed land, <hi>to the Eaſt, Weſt, North, and South, with the Plaines, Mountaines, and Seas;</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſatisfied, becauſe <hi>his eie was not dim.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſua, 18, 8, 9.</note> And whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the land was <hi>Topographically</hi> to be <hi>deſcribed,</hi> to giue vnto ſeuerall men their inheritances, the Suruaiors preſented their plots to <hi>Ioſhua,</hi> the Captaine of the Lords host; who, by Gods authoritie, ſhould quiet all questions that might ariſe by ſtriuers. But when I climed the <hi>Piſgah</hi> of the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uelation,</hi> where might bee taken the <hi>perſpectiue</hi> of the land, that <hi>Chriſt,</hi> with his holy people, ſhall poſſeſſe, by the preaching of the Goſpell; taking due notice of the dimnes of mine eies, I ſubmitted all my labour to your Lordſhippes true, and perfect ſight, and cenſure.</p>
            <p>And now, hauing drawne a plot of one particular place thereof, labouring to put the ſeuerall tenures, in their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers, yet proper colours, (ſeeing the importunitie of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would not ſuffer me to ſecreate it) I doe humbly returne
<pb facs="tcp:241:3"/>my ſuruey, not onely to your Lordſhips cenſure; but alſo to your most fatherly and Chriſtian patronage. Humbly cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing your good Lordſhip, (ſeeing all the tenants will neuer be pleaſed with my doing) both to defend me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cauils, and calumniations of the contentious, (of whoſe fury I haue had too much experience:) and alſo to interpoſe your honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable authority, that all men may content themſelues with theyr owne lots. My skill is ſmall, &amp; therfore I deſire the iuſt to reproue mee, where my hand, or eye hath fayled: but I dare be bold to ſay, that, in that which I was able to doe, I haue been faithfull. If your Lordſhip vouchſafe me this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable fauour, to accept, and protect my labours, I ſhall be much encouraged to take the like paines in the rest: I hope, to the glory of almightie God, the benefite of his Church, &amp; demonſtration of my dutie vnto your good Lordſhip, whom God euermore preſerue vnto eternall happines. <hi>Ianu: 25. 1606.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Lordſhips moſt humble in all Chriſtian obedience,</hi> VVilliam Symonds.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:241:3"/>
            <head>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A heauenly voyce.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reuelar: 18.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>And I heard another voyce from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſay, Goe out of her my people, that ye be not par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of her ſinnes, and that yee receiue not of her plagues.</p>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Reuelar: 18.5.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For her ſinnes are come vp to heauen, and God hath remembred her iniquities.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen the Lord would proue himſelfe to be GOD, and all that is worſhipped be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides him to be vanitie, he chuſeth men to be his Iudges, and witneſſes; and the iſſue to be,<note place="margin">Eſay, 41, 23.</note> that he that can <hi>ſhewe things to come hereafter, ſhould be knowne to be God.</hi> Then doth he referre himſelfe to themſelues,<note place="margin">Eſay, 44, 7.</note> that <hi>none is like vnto him, that ſhall call, and ſhall declare it, and ſet it in order before him.</hi> By this argument hee conuicteth his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, to the time of the Apoſtles: who were his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that <hi>all things were befallen Christ, which God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore had ſhewed by the mouth of all his Prophets.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Acts, 3, 18,</note> And by this argument he conuicteth all tyrants,<note place="margin">Chap, 10, 7,</note> and heretickes of the later, &amp; moſt perilous times, in this booke, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb facs="tcp:241:4"/>before hand,<note place="margin">Cap. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>to his ſeruants, thinges preſent, and to come.</hi> And this ſo perfectly, that <hi>Nothing can be added thereto,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 22, 18, 19</note> 
               <hi>neither any thing diminiſhed from the wordes of this prophecie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the former part of this Booke, was handled the ſtory of the Church, which for her ſinnes, and tryall, was, from time to time, <hi>troden vnderfoote</hi> by her ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold enemies,<note place="margin">Cap: 2, 5, 10 16, 22, &amp;c. and cap. 3, 3, 19,</note> according as the Lorde had threatned, and foreſhewed in the ſecond and third Chapters. And this is it which is contained from the beginning to the 15 verſe of the 11 chapter. Thence, to the end of that Chapter, is the prophecie of the better eſtate of the Church, both deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the handes of her enemies, deſtroying them that deſtroy the earth, and reuiuing the <hi>couenant of Grace,</hi> againſt all oppoſitions, vnto the ruine of <hi>Antichrist.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the ſecond part of this Booke, beginning at the 12 chap: the Lorde doth giue the Church a more preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant demonſtration of her enemies, and their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings againſt her, that they may be the better knowne vnto her.<note place="margin">Cap. 12, 3.</note> They are therefore deſcribed by the <hi>Dragon,</hi> preſenting the heathen <hi>Romane</hi> Empire, the monſter compounded of <hi>three beaſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 13.1.</note> (which cannot be tamed by any art of man) that riſeth out of the ſea: and ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth the <hi>Romane</hi> Empire corrupted with the hereſie of the <hi>Arians:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 13, 14.</note> and the <hi>Image</hi> of them both, preſenting the <hi>Antichristian</hi> eccleſiaſticall <hi>Monarchie</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> There is alſo ſhewed the manner of their preuailing againſt her, and howe they are ouercome, vnto the ſeauenth verſe of the 20 chapter.<note place="margin">Cap. 13, 3,</note> The ſecond <hi>beaſt,</hi> is deſtroyed with the ſword of many Nations. The third, namely the eccleſiaſticall Monarchie, called alſo <hi>Babilon,</hi> the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage
<pb facs="tcp:241:4"/>of the ciuile Monarchie, is brought to naught by the preaching of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> and by the <hi>iudgements of God</hi> inflicted vpon her for <hi>his ſeruants</hi> ſakes, whom ſhe hath killed. And this is generally declared in the 14.15 and 16 chapters, but more particularly in the 17 &amp; 18 chapters. And becauſe this wicked popiſh <hi>Antichriſtian beast,</hi> required ſo diligent a deſcription of her perſon &amp; ſinnes, that the Saints might be deliuered from ſo pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous a temptation; that point is effectually handled in the 17 chapter; inſomuch, that the Papiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues are enforced to acknowledge her to be <hi>Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this chapter are ſhewed the meanes, and manner of her deſtruction. The meanes by which her enemies are encouraged to bring her plagues vpon her, are two ſpeciall doctrines of the word of God, preuailing with Prince and people. <hi>Princes</hi> conuerted to the Goſpell, (figured <hi>by a mightie Angel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap, 18, 1, 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>that enlighteneth the earth with the glory</hi> of the Goſpell) doe iudicially decree, that Popiſh <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall fall into a damnable eſtate, for her great ſinnes. Namely, firſt for troubling of ſtates; ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, for corruption in doctrine, with which ſhee hath poyſoned other Nations; thirdly, for the immo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate riches of her Merchants, who ſold both iuſtice, and the ſoules of men. Both Prince and people that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey the <hi>Goſpell of the kingdome,</hi> ſhall bring her plagues vpon her at once, by embracing, and vrging a double doctrine of exhortation; and that is it which is contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my text.</p>
            <p>Of this doctrine, firſt is ſhewed the place fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence it commeth; to wit, the Temple of <hi>God,</hi> and his <hi>Christ,</hi> euen the ſincere profeſsion of the Goſpel; which in this booke, in a manner, continually is called by the name
<pb facs="tcp:241:5"/>of <hi>Heauen.</hi> Here then, all godly men, both Prince and people doe ioyne together in thoſe wholſome admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Lord. So that thoſe of the ſpirit of S. <hi>Iohn,</hi> who can well vnderſtand the things that are ſpoken, do heare theſe heauenly doctrines enforced by them. And this is the meaning of theſe words; <hi>And I heard another voyce</hi> (from that which Princes decreed for their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate benefite) <hi>from heauen, ſay.</hi> The matter of the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation is double; firſt to forſake her, euen this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> and then to purſue her with iuſt reuenge. The doctrine, or exhortation to forſake her, hath the propoſition, and the arguments to enforce it. The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition hath the parties admoniſhed, and their dutie. Their dutie is to <hi>flie from</hi> this confuſed and curſed <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon</hi> of poperie, in theſe wordes, <hi>Goe out of her.</hi> The parties on whom this <hi>heauenly voyce</hi> doth vouchſafe to beſtow theſe <hi>holy things,</hi> are no <hi>deafe Adders,</hi> but onlie ſuch which by Gods election doe belong to God: and by the couenant which they make, and holde, and by theyr ſufferings, for his ſake, are knowne ſo to do. And therefore the <hi>voyce</hi> of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt the Lord,</hi> by his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunts, doth call them <hi>from heauen, My people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The reaſons why they ſhould forſake her are two; both drawne from manifeſt perill. The firſt is the perill of contagion, and defiling themſelues with touching this pitch, in theſe words; <hi>That ye be not partakers of her ſinnes.</hi> The ſecond is the perill of vengeance to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted vpon her, and all her complices, in theſe wordes, <hi>and that ye receiue not of her plagues.</hi> This argument of her plagues is further enforced; &amp; is proued to be hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie and certaine; firſt, by the iuſtice of God, that requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth great ſinnes to be greeuouſly puniſhed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb facs="tcp:241:5"/>ſeeing her ſinnes exceede, it is not poſſible to hope for ſparing. The greatneſſe of her ſinnes, is expreſſed in an vſuall prouerbiall ſpeech of the Scripture, when it is ſaid, <hi>for her ſinnes are come vp to heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon to prooue her plagues to be cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, is the diligence that GOD now vſeth, in laying together her faults, that ſhee may receiue for euery one of them, that which ſhee hath deſerued; and that is the purpoſe of theſe wordes; <hi>and God hath remembred her iniquities.</hi> And thus much of the interpretation of the firſt doctrine of exhortation to the people of God. It remaineth that wee proceede to informe our conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces hereby.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>I heard another voyce from heauen.</hi> Heere we ſee, that thoſe of the ſpirit of S. <hi>Iohn, Doe heare the voyce that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quireth men to ſeparate themſelues from Babylon, and to reuenge themſelues of her, to come from heauen.</hi> By <hi>hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> in this booke for the moſt part, is not vnderſtood the place whether our Lorde and Sauiour is aſcended,<note place="margin">Acts. 1, 11,</note> but the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregation of the faithfull, profeſſing the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell of Chriſt, in his Church, where himſelfe is in the middeſt. For in the fourth chapter, where S. <hi>Iohn</hi> doth ſee <hi>a throne ſet vp in heauen, about which are</hi> 24 <hi>ſeates,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 4, 2, 4</note> 
               <hi>and</hi> 24 <hi>elders ſitting vppon them,</hi> in the 5 chapter theſe <hi>Eders</hi> doe praiſe <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 5.10.</note> 
               <hi>that had made them Kinges and Prieſts vnto God, that ſhould raigne on the earth.</hi> And this is proportionable to the reſt of the Scriptures, which doe call the Church of <hi>Christ, heauenly Ieruſalem;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ephe, 2, 6,</note> and the <hi>kingdome of heauen;</hi> and thoſe that are conuerted thereto, are ſaid to be made to <hi>ſit together in heauenlie places.</hi> The meaning is, that thoſe of the ſpirit of Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> doe heare this heauenly doctrine of God, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
<pb facs="tcp:241:6"/>taught among them that do ſincerely profeſſe the Goſpell of <hi>Christ, Come out of her, &amp;c. Reward her &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heerevpon it doth followe, that the doctrine of <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration</hi> from this popiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the doctrine of <hi>reuenge</hi> to be inflicted vpon her, which is reduced into lawes by godly Princes, conuerted to the Goſpell; and which is dilligently taught by the Preachers of the word; and is put in execution by good and godly ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects, whether vnder Magiſtrats or priuate men, is to be acknowledged for none other but <hi>a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi> And when it is ſayd to be <hi>a voice from heauen,</hi> it appeareth that the doctrine is, and ought to bee eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as effectuall as if God did immediately ſpeake <hi>from heauen.</hi> So that it is all one, whether God from heauen, doth commaunde Noah to make and enter the <hi>Arke,</hi> or that an <hi>Angell bid Lot get him out of So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom;</hi> or <hi>Moſes</hi> importune the people to get them from the tents of <hi>Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> or the Prophets <hi>Iſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah</hi> and <hi>Ieremie,</hi> by their prophecies before hand, doe inſtruct both Prince and people, to teach, and obey this rule, <hi>Get out of Babylon;</hi> or the godly Princes, and Preachers exhort the people of God, to ſeperate them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from the <hi>Romane</hi> popiſh beaſt. Euery voice, in this kind, is of like weight and authoritie. We knowe that it is blaſphemed by theſe vndutifull <hi>Babylonians</hi> to be tirrannie in Princes; to be affectation of liberty, and ſpoyle in inferior Magiſtrates; to be faction, and igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and hereſie in Miniſters and people. So doe we alſo knowe, that whatſoeuer the deuill ſaith in theſe ſerpents: yet <hi>Saint Iohn</hi> and thoſe of his ſpirite, doe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge they heare this <hi>voice from heauen,</hi> euen from <hi>Ieſus Chriſt;</hi> teaching, and inſtructing the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation
<pb facs="tcp:241:6"/>of all faithfull people, out of his holy word, in the Church. Heere therfore let all Chriſtian Kings, Counſailors, Biſhops, and all Magiſtrates, remember the generall <hi>Canon</hi> of the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Heb: 12.25.</note> 
               <hi>See that yee diſpiſe not him that ſpeaketh: For if they eſcaped not which refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him that ſpake on earth, much more ſhal not we eſcape, if wee turne away from him that ſpeaketh from heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreouer, ſeeing this voice is <hi>from heauen,</hi> it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that whoſoeuer doth teach, by writing, or preaching; or doth aduiſe, in deliberations, that any other courſe is to be held, that theſe popiſh <hi>Babylonians</hi> are in ſome things to be yielded vnto, and that ſome more milde, and gentle proceedings towards them would doe better; ſuch I ſay, neither can truly, nor may iuſtly be commended, that this wiſdome deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth from aboue, but it is from belowe,<note place="margin">Iam: 3.15.</note> and <hi>is earthly ſenſuall, and diueliſh.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor: 6.14 &amp;c.</note> For they labour to reconcile the things which haue no agreement, as righteouſnes with vnrighteouſnes, light with darknes, <hi>Chriſt and Beliall,</hi> the belieuer with the infidell, the temple of God with idols; and doe with <hi>Saule</hi> deſire to ſpare <hi>Agag,</hi> whom God requireth to punniſh. Againe, if the <hi>voice</hi> be <hi>from heauen,</hi> it ſhall bee eſtabliſhed; they that ſpeake other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are falſe Prophets, and they that ſtriue againſt it, doe kicke againſt the pricke.<note place="margin">Act: 5.38.39.</note> Wherefore as <hi>Gamaliel</hi> faith, in another caſe, <hi>refraine your ſelues</hi> from oppoſing it, <hi>leaſt yee be found fighters againſt God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct: </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Come out of her my people.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 14.12. Ioſhu: 2 1.8 Iudg: 4.11 17. 1 King: 19.7</note> Heere firſt we ſee that <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the wicked are the children of God.</hi> A thing very commonly noted in the Scripture. <hi>Lot</hi> was in <hi>Sodom;</hi> Rahab in <hi>Iericho: Iaell</hi> among the <hi>Gentiles: Obadiah,</hi> that feared God greatly, and ſaued an hundreth of the
<pb facs="tcp:241:7"/>Lords Prophets, was the gouernor of <hi>Ahabs houſe:</hi> and to be ſhort, there were Saints of Caeſars houſhold, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen of Nero, that cruell monſter. For good ſeede, and weede growe vp together; and corne and chaffe are on the floore together.<note place="margin">Exod. 6,9.</note> Yea, we know that in <hi>Egypt</hi> were many <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> that could be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tented to liue ſtill, with the onions and fleſh pots of <hi>Egypt,</hi> &amp; in <hi>Babylon,</hi> were many <hi>Iewes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezec. 20, 32</note> that ſaid, <hi>We will be like the heathen and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of the countries.</hi> Yet were theſe the redeemed of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezec. 36, 26</note> and ſanctified by him. In this Booke, the ſame is often ſhewed to be the condition not onely of many godly <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> but alſo of the <hi>moſt glorious Church.</hi> For ſhee <hi>flyeth into the wildernes,</hi> beeing min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gled among the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and ſuch pretended <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> as followed the <hi>Antichristian Papacie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of this, doe ariſe many godly conſiderations. Firſt, that ſuch as thinke that it is not poſsible for <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians</hi> to liue vnder the gouernment of vnchriſtian Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernors, but that they muſt looſe the name of godlie men, and their number muſt not be called a Church, doe exceedingly bewray their ignorance, both of the Scriptures in generall, and of this booke of the <hi>Reuela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> in particuler. The Church of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> was a Church,<note place="margin">Reue. 2, 13</note> and <hi>a golden Candleſticke,</hi> though ſhee <hi>dwelt where ſatans throne was.</hi> Yea, that which is more, it had <hi>them that maintained the doctrine of Balam, that taught Balack to put a ſtumbling blocke, before the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Iſraell:</hi> and alſo thoſe that <hi>maintayned the doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine of the Nicolaitanes.</hi> And the Church, is <hi>clothed in the ſunne,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue, 12, 1, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>treadeth the Moone vnder her feete,</hi> and is <hi>crowned with twelue ſtarres: a Woman,</hi> and a glorious Church, and holy, though ſhe be <hi>fled into the wildernes,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:241:7"/>and mingled among the <hi>Antichriſtian Babylonians,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued of publique aſſembles, ſacraments, &amp; diſcipline, as doth appeare by this ſpeech; <hi>Come out of her my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi> So that heere I cannot but reproue the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> or rather the reuiued <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> which haue made a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration from vs, and our Church; which they cannot blame as guiltie of the ſinnes of <hi>Pergamus,</hi> or <hi>Sardis,</hi> or <hi>Corinth,</hi> which notwithſtanding are acknowledged to be churches, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues being our Iudges. Much leſſe are we guilty of the ſins of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> among who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were the people of God notwithſtanding. Sure their ignorance is much to be lamented, and their diſſoluing of <hi>Christian Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion</hi> to be deteſted, &amp; therefore to be auoyded.</p>
            <p>Secondly, heere we learne to aunſwere the Papiſts, that demaund of vs where our Church hath beene for theſe thouſand yeeres. It was among them, though they were not it, as the chyldren of <hi>Iſraell</hi> were in <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Kings, 17 and 24.</note> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> in <hi>Holah, and Habor, and in the Citties of the Medes:</hi> and you were tranſlated into their wonted places, as were the <hi>Aſſyrians</hi> into the cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of <hi>Samaria,</hi> the ſeate of the people of GOD. But they ſay, that the <hi>Iſraelies</hi> were knowne to be in <hi>Goſhen,</hi> during their ſeruitude in <hi>Egypt.</hi> The ſcripture that ſaith alſo that the <hi>Iewes</hi> in the <hi>captiuity</hi> were in <hi>Holah &amp; Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor, &amp; in the cities of the Medes,</hi> doth note the place. But as for your <hi>Goſhen, and Holah, and Habor,</hi> they were no where to be ſeen, by ſuch as were as ſharp ſighted as the <hi>Egyptians or Babylonians.</hi> To this I anſwer, firſt that it is no merueile, that they ſee not the godly among them, partly becauſe, like the deuill, they thinke that all is theyr owne, and neuer conſider <hi>Iob,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob, 1.8.</note> that is an <hi>vpright and a iust man, one that feareth God, and eſcheweth euill:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:241:8"/>and partly becauſe of this time, that the queſtion is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doth ſay, that the <hi>woman</hi> the Church,<note place="margin">Cap: 12.14.</note> was in <hi>the Wilderneſſe, nouriſhed from the face or ſight of the ſerpent;</hi> which for ſubtiltie and quicke ſight (whereof this <hi>Dragon</hi> taketh his name) may ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry neere be compared to the Papiſts. But they ſay, where were their aſſemblies, their ſacraments, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons with other ſeruices. As if there could bee no <hi>Iewes</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Amoc. 6.10</note> becauſe according to the prophecie, <hi>they durſt not remember the name of the Lord;</hi> as it doth alſo appeare in the booke of <hi>Eſter,</hi> wherein the name of the Lord is not once mentioned. Were <hi>Ester, Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decai,</hi> and the people that <hi>fasted</hi> and <hi>prayed</hi> no people of God?<note place="margin">Mare 7.6.</note> Or are the godly bound to bewray, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray themſelues, by <hi>casting holy things to dogs, and pearles before ſwine,</hi> to bring the graces of God in them into contempt; and themſelues into manifeſt perrill? Secondly, wee anſwere, that our Church was among them, themſelues being our Iudges. For when they tell vs with what difficultie they gat the title of ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, what maſculine oppoſition they found, when, at <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and in the ſecond counſell of <hi>Nice,</hi> they would erect <hi>the worſhip of the Dragon,</hi> by the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of idols; when they tell vs, by what arts, they wronge themſelues from the ſubiection of Princes; when they proclaime bloudie,<note place="margin">5 Deer: de haereſ: ad abolendum.</note> and blaſphemous lawes againſe ſuch as teach and beleeue any otherwiſe; then they teach or beleeue (for ſo do they define heretickes) when they bragge of the many fiers, and warres that they conſumed them by, and inſult of their conqueſts this way; they alſo tell vs, that ſuch as maintained the doctrine of the Apoſtles, and ſuch as <hi>worſhipped the
<pb facs="tcp:241:8"/>God of their fathers after the way which they call hereſie,</hi> were among them, perſecuted for the ſame doctrines, that we differ from them in: and therefore, by their owne confeſſion, our Church was among them, which in this place is called <hi>the people of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, heere wee learne that ſuch which doe liue among the Papiſts, though ſtained with ſome of their ſuperſtitions may be ſaued: but alwaies with limitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Firſt that their ſinne be of <hi>ignorance,</hi> &amp; not of <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 15.30.</note> for there remaineth no ſacrifice for the ſinnes of ſuch. And ſecondly, that though <hi>they be ſmitten in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the place of Dragons, yet must they not forget God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal: 44.17.20.</note> 
               <hi>nor deale deceiptfully with his couenant, &amp;c. Nor hold vp their hands to any ſtrange God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>The Lord calleth his people out of Babylon,</hi> now at hand to be deſtroyed, for her ſinnes. For the rule is generall, that the <hi>Iudge of all the earth will not ſlay the righteous with the wicked:</hi> as <hi>Abraham ſaith to God.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> For how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>extricable ſoeuer the perrill ſeeme to be,<note place="margin">2 Pet: 2.9.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth how to deliuer the godly out of temptation.</hi> The Churches of the old Teſtament, had heere of plentifull experience, when we reade that <hi>Noah</hi> was deliuered from the <hi>floud; Lot</hi> from the burning of <hi>Sodom:</hi> and diuers others from diuers other great dangers. The Churches alſo of the new Teſtament, haue found the hand of God nothing ſhortened. For beſides the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold deliuerances of the godly in the <hi>Acts</hi> of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> it is reported, that when <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, becauſe ſhe knewe not the day of her viſitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the godly were forewarned by a voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,<note place="margin">Euſeb: 3.5.</note> to get them from <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> to <hi>Pella,</hi> a Cittie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond <hi>Iorden,</hi> there to ſaue them ſelues.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:9"/>
            <p>The ſame mercie doth the Lord ſhew to his people. For purpoſing to bring a finall deſtruction vppon that <hi>Rome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 11, 8,</note> which <hi>crucified our Lord Ieſus,</hi> and after become that <hi>Antichriſtian Babylon, which is drunken with the blood of Saints,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 17, 6,</note> 
               <hi>and Martyrs of Ieſus,</hi> hee firſt, by <hi>a hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly voyce,</hi> calleth <hi>his people out of her.</hi> By this merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prouidence are riſen all the proteſtant Churches; and the ſame mercy will the Lord continue, till he hath drawne all his people from among them; and till hee bring vppon this <hi>Babylon,</hi> her <hi>last and greatest plagues.</hi> Heereby we know, that ſuch as fall vnto them, are ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together like <hi>Baals priestes,</hi> that none of them be wanting when God will haue them conſumed; &amp; they that are gained from them,<note place="margin">Luke, 3, 7</note> 
               <hi>are eſcaped from the venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance to come.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>The people of God must come out from her.</hi> What is heere meant by <hi>Babylon,</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence the people of God muſt come, there is no great doubt; for both the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts and wee doe agree,<note place="margin">Ributa in 14 Reue. no: 27. &amp;c.</note> that it ſignifieth <hi>Rome</hi> vnder <hi>Antichrist,</hi> which doth reuiue the ſinnes of the heathen Emperors: But the difference betweene vs, is, <hi>when</hi> ſhee is to be called <hi>Babylon.</hi> The circumſtances of the text, which doe conuict <hi>Rome</hi> to be the place, will alſo teach vs when ſhe is <hi>Babylon.</hi> She muſt of force be then <hi>Babylon,</hi> when ſhe is guiltie of the faultes for which this <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſaid to fall.<note place="margin">Supra. verſe 2, 2, 3.</note> Her firſt ſinne is, that <hi>All Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue drunken of the Wine of the wrath of her fornica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi> That is, that all Nations haue beene afflicted, with warres, treaſons, cruelties, and diuers other cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, becauſe they would not ſubmit themſelues to to her abhominable pride, idolatrie, and other ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all fornications.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:9"/>
            <p>Secondly, when the Kings of the earth <hi>hane com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted fornication with her,</hi> corrupting themſelues, and theyr kingdomes with filthy ſuperſtitions, and wicked inuentions, which they haue fetched from her. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, when <hi>the Merchants of the earth are waxed rich, of the abundance of her pleaſures,</hi> getting much mony by ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling iuſtice, and the ſoules of men.</p>
            <p>Nowe becauſe <hi>Rome</hi> hath been guiltie of theſe three impieties, for the moſt part, theſe thouſand yeeres (as the many lamentable examples doe make demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but eſpecially in theſe later dayes, before and in the age in which wee liue,) wee doe confidently, and demonſtrably conclude, that <hi>Rome,</hi> for theſe thouſand yeeres paſt, hath beene; and eſpecially in the time in vvhich wee liue nowe is, the <hi>Babylon</hi> from whence the people of GOD is to come. The rule is generall, that all godly men, ought, at all times, to ſeperate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from the wicked. For thus ſaith Saint <hi>Paule,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Cor, 6, 17</note> 
               <hi>Come out from amongst them, and ſeperate your ſelues, (ſaith the Lord) and touch no vncleane thing, and I will receiue you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But as the dangers haue been the greater, ſo haue the vvarnings beene more importunate. Wherefore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Babylon,</hi> for her many cruelties &amp; corruptions, was <hi>worthy to be deſtroyed,</hi> Prophets <hi>Iſaiah</hi> and <hi>Ieremie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal, 137, 8,</note> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared many parables, for thoſe that came after, in due time, to drawe the people of GOD from thence, the plaee of the greateſt danger. The ſame wordes which theſe Prophets vſed, to draw the poſteritie of <hi>Iacob</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that firſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> doth S. <hi>Iohn</hi> heere vſe, to vvithdrawe the people of God fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this ſecond <hi>Babylon,</hi> more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous then euer was that firſt.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:10"/>
            <p>Heerevpon it followeth, that what were the ſinnes, and cruelties of that firſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> the ſame are iuſtly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to this ſecond <hi>Babylon:</hi> What perill the <hi>Iewes</hi> there were in, the ſame are the people of God in here; &amp; what equitie, by reaſon of the condition of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, or iniquitie of the oppreſſors, induced the <hi>Iſrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> to depart from <hi>Babylon,</hi> the ſame is to preuaile with <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to depart from this <hi>Antichriſtian Babylon of Rome.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was a curſed miſerie for the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> in the captiuitie, to be ſpoken vnto in <hi>a ſtrange language, and with a ſtammering tongue:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay, 28, 11</note> But in this <hi>Babylon,</hi> the whole religion is in a ſtrange tongue. Wherefore, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtrange tongues are a <hi>ſigne to them that belieue not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14.22.</note> it is a ſigne, that they whom God hath deliuered ouer to theſe, which ſpeake theſe ſtrange tongues, are in the condemnation of Infidels. The people of God among the <hi>Babylonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 50, 6,</note> were loſt ſheepe: But heere, they that follow this Beaſt, are in the caſe of reprobates, <hi>Whoſe names are not written in the booke of life of that Lambe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reue. 13, 8,</note> In the firſt <hi>Babylon, the ſhepheards</hi> of Gods people <hi>cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them to goe aſtray:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem, 50, 6</note> but heere, theyr ſhepheards like the <hi>Scribes and Phariſes, compaſſe ſea and land to make one of their profeſsion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 23, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and when hee is made, hee is made two folde more the child of hell, then themſelues:</hi> bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them to meditate, and commit treaſons, and to be hanged when they haue doone.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All that found the people of God in Babylon, deuoured them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ierem. 50, 7.</note> 
               <hi>and theyr enemies ſaid, We offend not, becauſe they haue ſinned againſt the Lord:</hi> But heere, as many as are knowne, or ſuſpected, to differ from them, are deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, bodie,<note place="margin">5 Deer. de haereſibus.</note> and ſoule, and goods, and name, &amp; friends.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:10"/>
            <p>And heere, I cannot but let them that are ſeduced know, that now, they ſuffer many of them to diſcourſe of Religion, at theyr tables, and in markets, and other meetings; whom, if they catch ſo dooing, where they haue power in theyr handes, or ſhall finde ſo dooing in theyr natiue Country, when they ſhall haue preuailed, ſuch diſcourſers muſt to the pot, and ſuffer as heretikes, notwithſtanding now they ſpeake the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fayre for a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, and for a while. Wherefore, <hi>flee from the mids of Babell, and depart out of the Land of theſe popiſh Calde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 50, 8, Eſay, 52, 2, 3, 11.</note> 
               <hi>and bee yee as the hee goates before the flocke. Looſe the bands from thy necke, ô thou captiue daughter. They that rule ouer the people of God, make them to howle. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, depart yee, goe out from thence, &amp; touch no vncleane thing, goe out of her, and be ye cleane, that beare the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the Lord. Come cleaue vnto the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere, 50.5,</note> 
               <hi>in a perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all couenant, that ſhall neuer be forgotten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſhall not be with you, as it was with the children of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> that came out of <hi>Egypt</hi> vppon a ſuddaine. <hi>For yee ſhall not goe out with hast, nor depart by flying away:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay, 52, 32,</note> 
               <hi>but the Lord will goe before you, and the God of Iſraell will gather you together.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay, 28, 17,</note> 
               <hi>The Lorde thy God will teach thee to profit, and leade thee by the way that thou ſhouldeſt goe.</hi> Hee will teach you the feare of the Lord, and inſtruct you by his holy word, to eſcape the moſt vnprofitable doctrines of ſuperſtitions, and treaſons, which directly tend to the deſtruction of body and ſoule, and are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enforced vppon you, by fables, and lyes; euen by ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prophecies of alterations, and hopes, which ſhall neuer bee accompliſhed.<note place="margin">Zac. 14, 12,</note> For this <hi>ſhall bee the plague where-with the Lord will ſmite all people, that haue fought against Ieruſalem,</hi> euen the profeſſion of the Goſpell of
<pb facs="tcp:241:11"/>
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb: 12.22.</note> 
               <hi>theyr fleſh ſhall conſume away, though they ſtand vpon their feete, and their eies ſhall conſume in their holes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſca: 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>and their tongue ſhall conſume in their mouth. They are fed with the wind, and follow after the eaſt wind, they increaſe daily lies, &amp; diſtruction.</hi> But if yee will imbrace the Goſpell,<note place="margin">Iohn. 17.17. Reue: 7.17.</note> the <hi>word of truth,</hi> the <hi>Lambe which is in the mids of the throne ſhall gouerne you,</hi> euen the godly and <hi>Chriſtian</hi> King ſhall <hi>leade you to the</hi> Scriptures <hi>the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of liuing waters, and God ſhall wipe all teares from your eies.</hi> Moreouer, when it is ſayd by <hi>a voice from heauen; come out of her my people,</hi> it is the office of as many as belong to <hi>heauen:</hi> be he King, or Biſhop, or Miniſter, or Magiſtrate, by enticing, as God did the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> from <hi>Egypt,</hi> by <hi>thrusting</hi> out, as the Angels did <hi>Lot</hi> from <hi>Sodom;</hi> by importuning, as <hi>Moſes</hi> did the people from the tents of <hi>Korah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram:</hi> or by <hi>pulling them out of the fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iud: 23. Zach: 3.2.</note> as God did <hi>Iehoſhuah,</hi> to call to them that belong to God, to come out from this <hi>Babylon</hi> of poperie, which is horrible for ſinne, and to be made horrible by deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And ſo much the rather, becauſe the enemie is proud. They inſult to ſee the ſlacknes of the Miniſtery, that are nothing ſo dilligent to ſaue, as they are to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy; they inſult for the generall coldnes, if not Apoſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, that is in the gentlemen, and their inclination to them wards; they inſult that the commiſſions againſt them, doe find ſo many failings; they inſult for diſcord, their auncient helper; they inſult that though the face of the lawe bee againſt them, yet the edge is turned from them. Wherefore let them ſee, that euery hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenly voice, of this Land doth crie, <hi>come out of her my people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 2.4.</note> and <hi>ſaue your ſelues from this froward generation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:11"/>
            <p>And heere I might haue paſſed to another point, were it not for the <hi>Brownistes,</hi> that abuſe this place to maintaine their wilfull ſinne,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.25.26.</note> in <hi>for ſaking the fellowſhip that we haue among our ſelues.</hi> Let them conſider, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the circumſtances of this text, and the like, where <hi>Babylon</hi> is mentioned in this booke, or the Prophets, whence Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> doth borrow his ſpeech, may truly agree to our Church, which maintaineth ſo many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions vnto <hi>Antichristian Babylon.</hi> Nay, if it may be prooued, that we haue departed from as many cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions, in doctrine and pollicie, as did conclude <hi>Rome to be Babylon;</hi> and haue imbraced as many doctrines, as did the children of <hi>Iſraell</hi> that came out of <hi>Babylon;</hi> ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther muſt they find vs another <hi>Babylon</hi> among the <hi>Iewes,</hi> departed from the captiuitie; or elſe their ſeper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation is an Apoſtaſie and no departure from <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Popiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> like the firſt <hi>Babylon,</hi> was builte by ſuch, whereof <hi>one did not vnderſtand anothers ſpeech;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen: 11.7. Beda Eccleſ. hiſt: Lib: 1. cap: 15.27. Act: 2.11. Amos. 6.10. Cap: 13.6.</note> but with vs, as in the times of the <hi>Apostles, all men doe heare in theyr owne tongues the wonderfull things of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Among the <hi>Babylonians,</hi> it was not lawful for the children of God <hi>to remember the name of the Lord;</hi> but we teach all men <hi>to reuerence the ſanctuarie of the Lord,</hi> and them that worſhip therein according to the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. In <hi>Babylon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dani: 3.2.3. Reue: 13.15</note> the people of God were vnder a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Tyrant, &amp; were conſtrained to <hi>worſhip the image of the beast,</hi> vnder paine of death; but we are deliuered from that captiuitie, and now the Lord is <hi>our God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech: 34.24.</note> 
               <hi>and his ſeruant Dauid</hi> (a Prince of our owne Nation) <hi>is our King;</hi> as the Lord did promiſe. Who ſeeth not then, that we are the people of God, <hi>come out of Babylon;</hi> &amp; therefore they <hi>that are departed</hi> from vs, <hi>haue erred in
<pb facs="tcp:241:12"/>their hearts, becauſe they haue not knowne the wayes of God,</hi> and doe <hi>blaſpheme</hi> when they call vs <hi>Babylon.</hi> But my purpoſe is to vrge that onely, which directly Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> would haue vs purſue.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>That yee be not partakers of her ſinnes.</hi> Here firſt is to be marked, that <hi>ſuch as will not depart from them, ſhall be infected by them:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 13,1</note> as it is ſaid, <hi>Hee that toucheth pitch, ſhall be defiled there-with.</hi> The rule is generall, ſinne is infectious, and this not onely with vnrighteouſnes, but alſo with impietie.<note place="margin">Prou, 22.25</note> 
               <hi>Make no friendſhippe with an angry man, &amp;c. leaſt thou learne his wayes,</hi> ſaith <hi>Salomon.</hi> But in matters of Religion, a man is exceeding weake, and the temptation mightie; ſo that a man ſoone learneth theſe wicked waies. Therefore did the Lord, ſo often, by <hi>Moſes,</hi> &amp; ſo earneſtly, by <hi>Ioſhua</hi> forewarne the <hi>Iewes</hi> to <hi>make no compact with the Nations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod, 23, 33 and 34, 15 Deu, 7, 2, &amp;c Ioſua, 23, 13</note> 
               <hi>and inhabitants of the Land, leaſt they ſhould be vnto them a ſnare, to cauſe them to ſerue other Gods.</hi> And as it was fore-told, ſo fell it out, as it is in the <hi>Pſalme. They were mingled among the heathen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 106, 35</note> 
               <hi>&amp; learned their works.</hi> But more perilous is this time of <hi>Antichriſt:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Tim. 3, 1 2, Theſ. 2, 11</note> becauſe in it, the Lord doth <hi>ſend ſtrong deluſion,</hi> ſo that <hi>if it were poſsible, the elect ſhould be deceiued.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 22, 24 Reue, 13.8,</note> No maruel the, if all thoſe <hi>whoſe names are not written in the booke of life, do follow the beast.</hi> And to iuſtifie the truth heereof, wee daily ſee many looſe fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes, practiſing, &amp; vndutifull wits, that meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon an alteration, to be daily ſeduced by the Popiſh prieſts, which ſwarme in the Land. Inſomuch that it is to be ſuppoſed, not onely by the wit of man, but alſo by the Word of God, that except ſome ſpeedie <hi>voyce come from heauen,</hi> to commaund the people to <hi>come out from her:</hi> and that the Lord ſend ſome <hi>mightie</hi> North
<pb facs="tcp:241:12"/>wind, <hi>to take away theſe Popiſh frogs, which are the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits of deuils,</hi> theſe trayterous <hi>Ieſuites</hi> and <hi>Prieſtes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 16, 13,</note> and violently to <hi>cast them into the ſea,</hi> without all queſtion,<note place="margin">Exod: 10.19</note> many ſubiects will partake in the traiterous ſinnes, of this <hi>Babylonian</hi> tyrannie. Their ſinne is, <hi>That as many as will not worſhip the beast, the</hi> Pope, <hi>must be killed.</hi> For this doctrine,<note place="margin">Reue, 13, 15</note> the <hi>ſpirit of the beast</hi> dooth continually inforce by all meanes, what euer other pretence hee make.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>6</label> Beſides, when it is ſaid, <hi>Least yee be partakers of her ſinnes,</hi> heere it is further ſhewed, that <hi>the people of GOD must not communicate with the ſinnes of this Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Babylon.</hi> The rule is generall, that the godly muſt not partake with any ſinners, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Ephe, 5, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Haue no fellowſhip with the vnfruitfull workes of darknes.</hi> And againe, <hi>Come out from among them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2, Cor, 6, 17</note> 
               <hi>and touch no vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane thing.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">Iude, 23,</note> 
               <hi>Hate the garment that is ſpot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the fleſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this purpoſe did <hi>Chriſt</hi> admoniſh his Diſciples, not to partake with the wicked Clergie of his time, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>Take heede of the leuen of the Pharaſies, and Saduces,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat, 16, 12,</note> meaning their euill <hi>doctrine,</hi> &amp; <hi>Woluiſh conditions.</hi> And Saint <hi>Paul</hi> requireth to hold <hi>an Angell,</hi> or <hi>Apostle,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gala. 1, 8, 9,</note> or any other man, accurſed, that bringeth in any other doctrine, then was at firſt receiued. What meruaile is it then, if Saint <hi>Iohn,</hi> in ſo perrilous and damnable a time as this, when the <hi>holie Cittie is become an harlot,</hi> yea, a Tyrant, and head of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> proude <hi>Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, Rome,</hi> a Cittie drunken with the blood of the <hi>Saints,</hi> if (I ſay) hee forbid all people to partake in her barbarous, blaſphemous, and couetous ſinnes, directly contrarie to the ſaluation of body and ſoule.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:13"/>
            <p>It ſeemeth a heauie, and grieuous thing, to depart from the conſent of ſo many Nations, and ages; and to be eſteemed ſciſmaticall: But when the commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement of God, doth require vs, not to ioyne hand in hand with the wicked to euill, but to come out <hi>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon,</hi> the commaundement doth miniſter vnto vs a iuſt Apologie before men, and ſtabliſh the conſcience be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to be innocent, and defenſible, in this ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. What are the ſinnes of this popiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> is partly to bee gathered out of <hi>Daniell, Iſaiah, Ieremiah, Ezechiell,</hi> and other ſcriptures, where mention is made of <hi>Babylon.</hi> For when <hi>Rome</hi> is heere called <hi>Babylon,</hi> we haue this libertie, to impute the cruelties, &amp; other ſius of the former <hi>Babylon,</hi> to this.</p>
            <p>In this booke more eſpecially, are mentioned theſe ſinnes,<note place="margin">Reu, 9.20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>Idolatry, murther, ſorcerie, fornication, theft,</hi> and theſe are further explaned in other places of this booke. In the tenth chapter her ſinne is, when Princes haue <hi>ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red as Lyons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 10, 3, 4.</note> to keepe the poſſeſſion of the people and ſoyle, to cry them downe with <hi>thundring execrations,</hi> and excommunications.<note place="margin">Cap. 11, 7,</note> In the 11, to make war with <hi>the witneſſes of Ieſus, when they haue finiſhed their testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie.</hi> In the thirteene it is ſaid,<note place="margin">Cap. 13, 6, 7</note> that <hi>hauing got power to ſpeake, and doe,</hi> what her lift, ſhe abuſeth her authoritie to <hi>blaſpheme,</hi> and <hi>to make warre with the Saints;</hi> euen to kill all <hi>that are not of</hi> her faction.<note place="margin">verſe 15.</note>
            </p>
            <p>All of her ſinnes may be reduced to theſe twoheades; <hi>The prophanation of the worſhip of God, and the barbarous ouerthrow of all charitable communion among men.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therefore wee are commaunded <hi>not to partake with her ſinnes,</hi> we are forbidden to defile the feare of God with any of her abhominations; or to diſſolue <hi>Christian
<pb facs="tcp:241:13"/>Communion</hi> with any of her cruelties; and oppreſſions. A man may partake in ſinnes, eyther by ioyning in the action, <hi>or by fauouring them that doe it.</hi> Wherefore,<note place="margin">Rom. 1. vit.</note> we are heere required, neither to ioyne with her, in any of her ſinnes, nor to fauour them that doe. Wee haue many in our Country that partake manifeſtly with this <hi>Romiſh Babylon,</hi> in her fornications and ſuperſtitions; as dooth appeare by the many ratles, idols, beades, and ſuch other trumperie, that are found co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually among them. Yea, we haue many that haue beene willing to miniſter the cup of the wine of the wrath of her forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, to Prince and people; as appeareth by the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie treaſons, which are attempted: and the correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of multitudes with the traytors. Yea, that which is more, there are found in England, (I had almoſt ſaide in London) ſchooles to traine vp Gentlemens chyldren, in this impious, &amp; rebellious religion, where the Gouernours diſclaime his ſacred Maieſtie, King <hi>Iames,</hi> to be theyr King, and profeſſe themſelues the Popes ſubiects. But the holy Ghoſt heere ſpeaketh to them all, <hi>Bee not partakers with her ſinnes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others happily there may be, euery way as peſtilent, who publiquely ſeeme to fauour the Goſpell, but co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertly, and vnderhand, fauour, and much further this vngodly, and peſtilent religion, playing faſt and looſe with the ſtate. Howe perilous this kinde of perſons is, may be ſeene in the ſtory of <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great. In his time, certaine ſuppoſed <hi>Arian</hi> conuerts, abuſing the ſinguler lenitie, and credulitie of the Emperour, inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated themſelues into the fauour of the Prince,<note place="margin">Socr. 1, 10, 18, &amp;c.</note> wrought themſelues into offices, and imployments in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth; they openly ſeemed to maintaine the
<pb facs="tcp:241:14"/>faith of the <hi>Nicaene</hi> Creede; but keeping their old cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruption, in theyr harts, by all meanes they could, colla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terally, with ſlaunders and iniuſtice, through the ſides of godly men, wounded the holy and innocent cauſe. I feare among the Iuſtices of the Land, &amp;c. may bee be found very many ſuch, euery way as preiuditiall to the Goſpell. Bleſſed be his mouth that ſaid, hee would remooue them, and put better in theyr roomes; and bleſſed be his hand that doth it. In the meane ſpace, this <hi>heauenly voyce</hi> dooth ſpeake to ſuch, <hi>Partake not with her ſinnes.</hi> And heerein it is required wee be the more circumſpect; becauſe her ſinnes are ſo ſubtile, that they enter in, and poſſeſſe many a man, which dooth ſeeme to himſelfe, and to others, to hold this filthy <hi>Babylon</hi> in ſingular abhomination. But it followeth in the next place.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>And that ye receaue not of her plagues.</hi> For ſuch as will continue in a place to be deſtroyed, muſt fcele the ſmart of the ſame deſtruction. <hi>Lots wife</hi> beeing deliuered fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Sodom,</hi> in compaſsion, would looke back towards her old neighbours, and was turned into a piller of ſalt. <hi>Remember Lots Wife,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 17.32</note> ſaith <hi>Chriſt.</hi> As her ſinnes are many and foule, ſo are her plagues very many and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie. For the better diſcouering of her ſinnes, ſhee is called <hi>the Image of the beaſt, which was wounded with the ſword,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 13, 14,</note> 
               <hi>and did liue,</hi> as hauing as many ſinnes, as were found in the Empire, whether corrupted by the <hi>Arians,</hi> or in the handes of the heathen Tyrants. Her plagues therefore are as many, as are the plagues of the enemies of the Goſpell, mentioned in this Booke.</p>
            <p>In the ſixt chapter, the contempt of the Word of God by the heathen,<note place="margin">Reue. 6, 8,</note> is puniſhed <hi>with ſword, mortality,
<pb facs="tcp:241:14"/>famine, &amp; beaſtes:</hi> kindes of plagues which haue much afflicted this popiſh <hi>beaſt.</hi> Wherefore we muſt know, that when the Land, or Cittie is puniſhed with warres, or murthers, with famine or peſtilence, or other mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie, it is for the ſinne of ſuch as partake in the <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian</hi> ſinnes, of the contempt of the Word of God. For inſtance, this Cittie, When vpon the death of the late <hi>Queene,</hi> worthy of eternall memorie, it became to giue entertainement, and reſt, to ſuch which plotted treaſons, and drifted the rooting out of the Goſpel, did lately feele the ſcourge of peſtilence, <hi>the Pale horſe:</hi> ſince haue we beene threatned with the ſhaking of the <hi>great ſword of him that ſitteth on the redde horſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 6, 4.</note> And if wee repent not, by our more zealous embracing of the Word of GOD, which ſitteth vpon the <hi>white horſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe, 2,</note> and by <hi>comming out from among</hi> the popiſh enemies therof, we may feare the experience of <hi>Famine,</hi> that ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth on the <hi>black horſe.</hi> In other places of this booke, the plagues of this <hi>Babylon</hi> are <hi>wofull,</hi> by the incurſion of fieree ſtrangers; by the continuall warres with vnre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concileable &amp; mortall enemies; by the ſeuerity of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings; &amp; by the reprofe of the preachers of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.<note place="margin">Cap. 9. &amp; 10 and 11. Cap. 16.</note> In other places, are mentioned the plagues of <hi>ſores,</hi> of <hi>bloodſhed</hi> by <hi>ſea &amp; land,</hi> of <hi>vnſeaſonable and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempered ayres,</hi> of <hi>darkning her kingdome, &amp;c.</hi> When theſe things alſo come vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the places where the goſpell is profeſſed, we muſt know, that it is becauſe of the ſins of ſuch, as partake in the ſins of the <hi>Babylontan King A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baddon, the great Antichrist.</hi> I know the brags, &amp; lies of that Sect; They perſwade theyr damned <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> that in former times, before the dayes of Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (vvhoſe memorie bee alwaies bleſſed)
<pb facs="tcp:241:15"/>the times were peaceable, plentifull, holy, and of one minde with them. Howbeit, theyr owne Writers doe make demonſtration, that all the world beſides, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afford vs ſo many barbarous tragedies, vnſpeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able diſſentions, horrible impieties, lamentable deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and terrible iudgements from aboue. Inſomuch, that the earth, for giuing power to this <hi>Babylonian</hi> beaſt, hath fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> time to time beene <hi>ſmitten with all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of plagues.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 11, 6,</note> Then to deliuer our ſelues from ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny calamities, <hi>come out of her my people, and receaue not of her plagues,</hi> ſaith this <hi>heauenly voyce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many haue thought it an excellent policie, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uent the euils that may come by barbarous heretickes, to come as neere vnto them as they can.<note place="margin">2, Reg. 16, 2 Chro, 28,</note> So is it ſaide of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> King of <hi>Iudah,</hi> that hee made an altar accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the faſhion of that of the <hi>Aramites of Damaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus,</hi> drew neere to the religion of the King of <hi>Aſhur,</hi> made peace with him, and gaue him large rewards. But all helped not. For when he called to him for ayde, hee <hi>did not ſtrengthen him, but afflicted him.</hi> Neither found the <hi>Iewes</hi> any better ſucceſſe, with drawing neer to the religion of the <hi>Cananites.</hi> For then did the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and other <hi>Gentiles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reade the book of the Iudges.</note> 
               <hi>tyranniſe</hi> ouer them moſt extreame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Thankes be to God, wee be vtterly departed, from this popiſh <hi>Babylon,</hi> in deede. Yet ſome very ſmall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed appearances, that they thinke wee partake with them in, haue cauſed them to be exceeding confident in their owne religion, as it were, by our teſtimonie; They deteſt our differences from them, and haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, that by one practiſe or other, of wit or force, we might eaſilie be reduced againe, full and whole to their ſubiection. Yea, they haue beene heereby much
<pb facs="tcp:241:15"/>exaſperated; but nothing reconciled, notwithſtanding their hypocriſies. By this, it may appeare how perrilous it is, as much as in the leaſt ſeeming to partake with her ſinnes. But if once all the Princes profeſſing the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, being cleane departed from her, did ioyne toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in that great <hi>Hallelu-iah,</hi> which <hi>Dauid</hi> prayeth for,<note place="margin">Pſal: 67.5.</note> when he ſayth, <hi>let all the people praiſe thee O God, yee let all the people praiſe thee:</hi> then ſhould they find the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that followeth; <hi>then ſhall the earth bring forth her increaſe, and God, euen our owne God, ſhall giue vs his bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi> For ſo do the godly ſing <hi>Hallelu-iah,</hi> becauſe God hath <hi>condemned the great Whore, which did corrupt the earth with her fornication.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap: 19.2.</note> Now the better to forewarne vs of her plagues, he ſheweth that they muſt needes be great.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>For her ſinnes are come vp to heauen.</hi> There is no ſinne ſo ſmall, which doth not come vp to heauen, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſight of God; euery <hi>teare is put in his bottell,</hi> and all <hi>theſe things are written in his booke.</hi> How be it, the Scripture is not wont to vſe this kind of phraſe, but whereas ſinnes doe ſo exceede, that their punniſhment cannot be deferred. So the cry of the ſinnes of Sodom are ſayd to <hi>come vp to God,</hi> that is, to be exceeding grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous.<note place="margin">Gen: 18. 20.21. 2 Chro: 28.9.</note> The ſinnes of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> for which he was captiued, were ſuch, that <hi>their rage</hi> is ſayd to <hi>reach</hi> vp <hi>to heauen;</hi> that is, to be exceſſiue; not only in the ſight of God, but alſo in the ſight of men. When finnes ſeeme ſmall, by reaſon of the groſſe ignorance that is in the world, it is one thing; but when, by the abundance of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, they appeare as they be, the caſe is otherwiſe; as <hi>Saint Paule</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Act: 17.30.</note> 
               <hi>the time of this ignorance God regar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not: but now he admoniſheth all men, euery where, to
<pb facs="tcp:241:16"/>repent.</hi> So, while the daies were darke, the groſſe ſmnes of the <hi>Antichristian Babylonians</hi> ſeemed very ſmall; nay the world did thinke them holy, and righteous. But now, that the <hi>maruelous light of the Goſpell doth ſhine;</hi> her ſinnes, which haue gotten a wonderfull incteaſe, are manifeſtly diſcerned to be heaped vp to heauen. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her ſinnes of crueltie, whereby ſhe iuſtifieth her elder Siſter, the firſt <hi>Babylon:</hi> both the law and the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, doe prooue <hi>her ſinnes to be heaped vp to heauen.</hi> The L'ord, in the law, doth ſeuerely condemne the <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of many Gods;</hi> but there neuer was Nation vnder the ſunne, that could be compared to this <hi>Antichristian Babylon,</hi> for multitude of Gods.</p>
            <p>The Lord did alwaies abhorre ſuch kinds of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, as him ſelfe had not preſcribed, which yet for the moſt part conſiſted in many friuolous obſeruances; but theſe haue not only defiled the worſhippe of God with abhominable inuentions; but alſo haue tranſlated the true, and ſpirituall worſhippe of God to creatures; nay to idols;<note place="margin">Petrus de Natale</note> nay to figments, as witneſſeth their fable of <hi>Saint George.</hi> It is a ſinne that God <hi>will not hold guiltles</hi> to <hi>take his name in vaine.</hi> But theſe, doe not only abuſe the name of God; but alſo God himſelfe; not only to vanitie, but alſo to the committing of the greateſt ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hominations; as to curſe Kings, and to ſtirre vp rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt them, by their Bulles. In the primitiue Church,<note place="margin">Plim: lib: 10. example: 97. Euſ: 3.30.</note> the <hi>Christians</hi> did aſſemble themſelues in the morning, praiſing <hi>Christ</hi> their God; and bound them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues with <hi>the ſacrament,</hi> not to commit adulterie, not to <hi>murther,</hi> not to bee perfidious, or <hi>trayterous;</hi> but theſe abuſe the Sacrament, which they call theyr God, &amp; their maker, to vnſpeakeable euils. For Pope <hi>Victor</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:241:16"/>the 2. was poyſoned in his Chalice, by his Deacon,<note place="margin">Genebrard. Chron. Paral. vrſp.</note> and <hi>Henrie</hi> the 7. the Emperour, was poyſoned by a <hi>Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can</hi> hypocrite, in the Sacrament. But now, they vſe the Sacrament to conuay the deuill into men, before ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what honeſt. For they do bind men by their <hi>Sacrament,</hi> to murther Princes, nobles, yea, the whole Parliaments, &amp; the whole Church of God. And their ſubiect, like <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das Iſcariot,</hi> who vpon <hi>receiuing of the ſop</hi> was ouerruled by <hi>the deuill to betray his Maiſter,</hi> doe reſolue vpon ſuch murthers; as the like is not to be found in the ſtories of the moſt infamous tyrants. And ſo <hi>their ſinnes are come vp to heauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the ſecond table, they teach not only children to diſhonor their parents, &amp; wiues to deſpiſe their huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands; but alſo ſubiects to rebell againſt their lawfull Princes. Yea, they thruſt out the lawfull heires, &amp; vfurpe the kingdoms &amp; Empire. They arrogate vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues power to plant and depoſe whom they liſt.<note place="margin">Diſt. 40. Si papa. in Gloſla De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponendus ſi minus vt: lis. Faſc. Tem. in Zach. 1.</note> The cauſe is counted ſufficient to depoſe a Prince, if hee <hi>be leſſe for their profit,</hi> and the cauſe is ſufficient to place who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they liſt, if he <hi>be more for their profit.</hi> They murther, and that in ſuch horrible maner, that they iuſtifie the moſt abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable perſecutors; withes be their indeuour to blowe vp the <hi>Parliament houſe,</hi> &amp; to fire citties,<note place="margin">Reade the maſſacre in Paris, anno. 1572.</note> to paue ſtreetes with dead carcaſſes, and to ſtaine great riuers with the blood of the ſlaine. They can giue you a reaſon, vvhy ſtewes of both kindes be profitable in a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon wealth. They teach it for good diuinitie, for thoſe of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, to rob the goods of the Proteſtants, which I take to be the cauſe that ſo many Papiſts be thieues. And I think the popiſh thieues, if they were demanded by the Iudge, would not let to cleare their co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences by their religion.
<pb facs="tcp:241:17"/>They condemne the memory of all godly men, &amp; ſo are the falſeſt witneſſes that euer trode vpon the earth. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, there is nothing ſo contrary to wholſome doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, which among them is not good diuinitie, if it may any way ſerue to aduance their greatnes. Yea, they haue turned that gracious rule,<note place="margin">1, Tim, 6, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>Godlines is great gaine,</hi> into <hi>Gaine is great godlines.</hi> And as they deale with the Law, ſo do they with the couenant of Grace. For they haue cleane left off <hi>to giue knowledge of ſaluation to the people, by the remiſsion of their ſinnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke. 1, 77 78.</note> 
               <hi>through the tender mercie of our God,</hi> in the blood of <hi>Ieſus Christ:</hi> and ſoules are bought &amp; ſold at a baſe price, of <hi>ſiluer, &amp; gold, &amp; corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1, Pet, 8, 18,</note> contrary to the words of S. <hi>Peter.</hi> Yea, for a ſmall price,<note place="margin">Guicciar. lib 13. an. 1520</note> &amp; ſomtimes are ſet vpon a game at tables, as a writer of their owne doth acknowledge. And while they thus make vile the blood of <hi>Christ,</hi> it may iuſtlie be ſaid, <hi>that her ſinnes are gone vp to heauen:</hi> and ſo beeing great, are neere vnto deſtruction. A ſecond reaſon to proue her plagues to be at hand, doth follow.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>9</label> 
               <hi>God hath remembred her iniquities.</hi> It is true, that in God is neither forgetfulnes, nor recalling to memorie. For <hi>all things are</hi> alwaies <hi>preſent,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb, 4, 13</note> 
               <hi>and naked, and bare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, with whom we haue to doe.</hi> But the Scripture ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of God after the manner of men, for our better vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding. Namely, that as men, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they purpoſe to right or reuenge the wrongs that are done them, do call enery partieuler to memory, the better to further theyr determination; ſo God, when hee purpoſeth to relieue his ſeruaunts, or puniſh his enemies, is ſaide to <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his Couenaunt, and to remember their ſinnes.</hi> So when the Lord doth intend to puniſh,<note place="margin">Hoſea, 8, 13 and 9, 9.</note> the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaith, <hi>The Lord will remember their iniquities, &amp; viſite their ſinnes.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:241:17"/>Wherefore, when heere it is ſaid, that <hi>God hath remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred her imquities,</hi> it muſt be ſupplied, and <hi>will viſite her ſinnes.</hi> As men haue their meanes to remember thinges forgotten, ſo God, by ſuch means, doth let it appeare he remembreth ſuch things, as men ſuppoſe he hath forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Men vſe to remember their wrongs, when they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the thinges in which they are wronged; ſo doth God remember the cruelties of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exod, 2.23 and 3, 9.</note> when hee beholdeth the burthens of his ſeruaunts, the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Againe, men call to mind, when they haue reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancers; ſuch vnto God, are his Prophets, &amp; Miniſters of his word &amp; Sacraments. For thus ſaith the Widdow of <hi>Zarephtah</hi> to <hi>Elias,</hi> when her ſonne was dead,<note place="margin">1, Kings, 17, 18,</note> 
               <hi>What haue I to do with thee thou man of God, art thou come to call my ſinnes to remembrance, and to fley my ſonne?</hi> But eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, men recall things to memorie, when the perſons that doe the wrong, doe renue their old manner of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefe. So doth God, when the wicked returne to theyr vomit, and ſo abuſe the patience of God, by prouoking him by the ſame ſins, which they ſeemed to haue broken off. Such are the ſins of the <hi>Romiſh Babilon</hi> here ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of,<note place="margin">Ribera in Apoc. cap. 14, and 18.</note> as the papiſts the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues confeſſe. For they ſay, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Rome</hi> ſhalbe guilty of the ſins of the heathen emperors, &amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutors which were before in her cruell daies, <hi>Then ſhall God remember her miquities preſent &amp; past.</hi> And indeed ſuch are Gods proceedings. For he threatneth the man, that leauing his ſm became righteous, that if he forſaketh his righteouſnes, <hi>he ſhal die for his tranſgreſsion &amp; ſin.</hi> vz.<note place="margin">Ezec. 18, 24</note> firſt and laſt. Now let euery man that hath any braines in his head, to iudge, or conſcience in his boſome to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thinges as they bee, conſider, and ſpeake, if hee can finde anie idolatrie ſo ſinfull, or crueltie
<pb facs="tcp:241:18"/>ſo barbarous among the greateſt heathen Emperors, or among the moſt beaſtly and bloody <hi>Arians,</hi> which may not be iuſtified, being compared with the ſpiritual forni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations of this <hi>Babylonian ſynagogue of Antichriſt,</hi> &amp; with her continuall <hi>drunkennes</hi> with the blood of the Saints. Wherfore, ſeeing the bloud &amp; aſhes, of milions of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Martyrs; &amp; the indignities &amp; treaſons offered to ſo many godly princes, doth cry for vengeance; ſeeing the faithful preaching, &amp; profeſsion of the goſpell, doth call for the aſsiſtance, &amp; teſtimony of the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of God; &amp; laſtly, ſeeing that her exceeding rage, &amp; violent mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, in committing the ſinnes of her abhominable impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eties, formerly condemned, doth repeate her ſinnes paſt, how can wee thinke, <hi>but God hath remembred her iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi> And, thanks be vnto almightie God, we ſee, at this time, the high court of Parliament, now, by the grace of God to be aſſembled, ſo effectually put in minde of her ſinnes, that if now, they do not awaken, it is to be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, that nothing wil awaken them, till it be too late. But wee hope, and earneſtly pray vnto almighty God to ſee ſuch lawes concluded, as well for the matter, as for the faithful maner of their executio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, both in this parliament, and alſo in the aſſemblies of other Princes abroad, that may proue, that <hi>God hath ſo remembred her iniquities;</hi> &amp; may make their harts to quake that <hi>partake in her ſinnes,</hi> becauſe they ſhall ſee no remedy, but to <hi>receiue of her plagues.</hi> The ſame Lord, which was <hi>wont to confirme the word of his ſeruants,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſay, 44, 26,</note> 
               <hi>&amp; performe the counſell of his Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers,</hi> bring this <hi>heauenly voyce</hi> to ſo happy an effect, euen for <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, who ſitteth at the right hand of his Father, till all his enemies be made his footeſtoole.</hi> And let all true <hi>Christians</hi> ſay <hi>Amen Amen.</hi> Hallelu-jah.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:241:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
